Guide to The Women's Sports Foundation Records 1950-2019 (bulk, 1974-2018) MS 3199
New-York Historical Society
Women's Sports Foundation records
1950-2019 (bulk, 1974-2018)
New-York Historical Society
Women's Sports Foundation
MS 3199
646 Linear feet in 645 record cartons and 1 flat box
5.62 Gigabytes (2,643 digital files)
The Women's Sports Foundation was established in 1974 by Billie Jean King to advance the lives of women and girls through sport and activity. The WSF serves as a source of information on women's and girls' sports and a national advocate for gender equality in sports by conducting and publishing research, providing grants to athletes and to sports and community programs, and holding events and conferences. The WSF records document the administrative history of the WSF, from its founding in 1974 to the 2010s. Records include meeting minutes and records of the Board of Trustees, staff files, research files, correspondence, publications, digital files, and collected reference files on girls' and women's sports. Subjects and topics of records include Title IX, equity in adolescent and college sports, athlete advocacy, and administrative and operational functions of the WSF over time. Material dates from 1950-2018, with bulk dates 1974-2018. Portions of the collection are not yet processed and are restricted, as noted in the finding aid.
Arrangement
Arranged in nine series:
Series I. Women's Sports Foundation archives
Series II. Board of Trustees records
Series III. Staff records
Series IV. Departmental records
Series V. Photographs
Series VI. womenSports magazine [RESTRICTED/ unprocessed]
Series VII. Audiovisual and digital formats [RESTRICTED/ unprocessed]
Series VIII. Artifacts [RESTRICTED/ unprocessed]
Series IX. WSF Library [RESTRICTED/ unprocessed]
Biographical / Historical
The Women's Sports Foundation was established in 1974 by Billie Jean King to advance the lives of women and girls through sport and activity. The Foundation was first established in San Francisco and supported by individual donations, corporate contributions, and fundraising events. Athletes Donna de Varona, Micki King, Joan Joyce, Wyomia Tus, Sheila Young, Jane Blalock, Paula Sperber, and Mary Jo Peppler were involved in the foundational discussions and early years of the Foundation. For the first two years, the main programs of the Foundation were to act as a central source of information and referral on women's sports, to assist girls' and women's groups in introducing sports programs, the sponsorship of a scholarship for girls' sports camps, and the coordination of seminars and clinics on sports and physical fitness.
In 1976 the first executive director Eva Auchincloss was appointed, and an Advisory Board composed of female athletes and individuals from sports-related fields was formed to set the goals and programs of the organization. It was decided that the WSF would become the national collective voice of women in sports and would work with and through sport and general interest organizations, would devise programs and activities that would help popularize sports and physical fitness for women, would provide a network for women in sports, and would provide a central source of information on women's sports. In 1977 the Foundation established its first grant programs and distributed its first official newsletter. In 1979 Donna de Varona became the first elected Foundation president.
Throughout the early 1980s, the Foundation initiated additional programs, grants, and research projects, including the International Women's Sports Hall of Fame launched in 1980, toll-free information phone line in 1981, internship program in 1982, first Travel & Training Fund grants awarded in 1984, and High School All-Star program in 1985. In 1983 the Foundation, along with the United States Olympic Committee, sponsored the New Agenda Conference, at which more than 500 of the most influential people in sports, education, and government gathered in Washington, DC to address issues of concern to women in sports. In 1985 the proposal for the Aspire Higher campaign to raise three million dollars for the Foundation was created, a Coaches Advisory Roundtable (CAR) was established, and the Foundation conducted its first research study, "The Miller Lite Report on Women in Sports."
In 1986 the WSF relocated to New York City and hired Deborah Slaner Larkin as the second executive director. In 1987 the first National Girls and Women in Sports Day (NGWSD) was held, thanks in part to the Foundation and to Senators Bill Bradley, Ted Kennedy, Bob Packwood, and Ted Stevens and Congresswomen Olympia Snowe and Claudine Schnieder. In 1990 Sudafed joined with the Foundation as the first corporate national supporter, enabling the Foundation to expand staff and programs.
In 1992 Donna Lopiano, former Athletic Director of Women Athletics at the University of Texas came on board as the new executive director. Lopiano developed the Community Awards and Grants program, later renamed the Community Action Program. In 1993 the Foundation moved its headquarters to Nassau County, New York (Eisenhower Park). In 1994 the Athletes' Speaker Service, later renamed the WSF Athlete Ambassador Program, was launched to raise the profile of female athletes and to educate and inspire the public. In 1996 the WSF launched its first website and a weekly email newsletter. In 1997 WSF published the Gender Equity Report Card, an exhaustive survey of athletic opportunities in higher education. In 1998 the Foundation was granted official United Nations Consultative status to the Economic and Social Council. In 2000 the Foundation was awarded the International Olympic Committee's first Women and Sport Award for the Americas. In 2001 the WSF launched the GoGirlGo! curriculum and educational campaign. Throughout 2003 the WSF helped to lead a 12-month campaign with a coalition of more than 100 organizations to engineer grassroots demonstrations in seven cities to oppose the administration's attempts to dismantle Title IX.
In 2008 the Billie Jean King International Women's Sports Center opened in New York City inside the Sports Museum of America. The Museum subsequently closed in 2009. From 2010 to 2014 the Foundation partnered with University of Michigan's School of Kinesiology and its Institute for Research and Women and Gender on the establishment and work of the Sport, Health and Activity Research and Policy (SHARP) Center for Women and Girls. In 2013 the International Olympic Committee selected the Foundation's GoGirlGo! Curriculum as a model for global youth sports programs. In 2004 the GoGirlGo! Education curriculum received a gold National Health Information Award from the Health Information Resource Center.
In 2014 the WSF and espnW co-founded Sports 4 Life, a program to address the racial disparities in access to youth sports opportunities for girls of color. In 2015 the WSF hosted its first Athlete Leadership Connection, an annual event connecting top industry leaders with professional and collegiate female athletes. In 2016 the WSF held its first "Candid Conversations" series to provide champion and college athletes with skills to advance their post-competition careers and held the 30th annual National Girls and Women in Sports Day (NGWSD). In 2020 WSF established The Equity Project, an initiative designed to close the gaps in equitable access and opportunities in sports and to achieve true gender equality.
As of 2021, the mission of the Foundation states, "We are the ally, advocate and catalyst for tomorrow's leaders. We exist to enable girls and women to reach their potential in sport and life."
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection are restricted, as noted in more detail at the series level.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Women's Sports Foundation, 2019.
Related Materials
Related artifacts and objects are held by the New-York Historical Society Museum. Inquiries about these objects can be directed to the Museum at: nyhscollections@nyhistory.org.
Scope and Contents
The Women's Sports Foundation records document the administrative history of the WSF, from its founding in 1974 to the 2010s. Records include meeting minutes and records of the Board of Trustees, staff files, research files, correspondence, digital files, publications, and collected reference files on girls' and women's sports. Records are organized by the originating administrative body, staff member, department, and material type. A discrete group of records labeled as the "WSF Archives" has been maintained and contains the core historical documentation and reference files for the WSF. Subjects and topics of records include Title IX, equity in adolescent and college sports, athlete advocacy, and administrative and operational functions of the WSF over time. Material dates from 1950-2018, with bulk dates 1974-2018.
Administrative records.; Digital file formats.; Letters (correspondence); Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Research (documents); Advertising, Public service.; Athletes -- United States.; Fund raising.; Nonprofit Organizations -- United States.; Sex discrimination against women -- Law and legislation.; Sports -- United States.; Sports for women.; Women -- Employment.; Women athletes.; United States -- Education Amendments of 1972 -- Title IX.; Women's Sports Foundation -- Administration.; Women's Sports Foundation -- Archives.; Auchincloss, Eva; King, Billie Jean; Lopiano, Donna A.
- Series I. Women's Sports Foundation archives, 1974-2018; 25 Linear feet in 25 record cartons
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes two groups of files originally stored in the WSF office in vertical filing cabinets labeled "WSF Archives" and "WSF Publications." These files were maintained by WSF staff as the core historical documentation and internal reference files for the organization. The "WSF Archives," or chronological files, includes early descriptions of the organization, annual reports, scholarship guides, coach and parent handbooks, reports and studies, event documents, and clippings. The publication archive includes WSF-produced official newsletters and magazines documenting WSF activities, priorities, and changes over time. Material in this series dates from the creation of WSF in 1974 to 2018.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Chronological files
  Subseries I.B. Publications archive
  - Subseries I.A. Chronological files, 1974-2018; 22 Linear feet in 22 record cartons
    Subseries I.A includes files originally stored in the WSF office in vertical filing cabinets labeled "WSF Archives." This group of material was maintained by staff as the core historical documentation of the organization. Files provide insight into the programming, structure, and goals of the Foundation over time. The earliest material includes the Foundation's "Statement of Purpose," newsletters, and member and subscriber surveys. Additional document types include the Foundation's newsletters, annual reports, annual scholarship guides, coach and parent guides, reports and studies, and newspaper clippings. WSF programs and events, particularly the WSF Annual Summit, New York Awards Dinner (NYAD), National Girls and Women in Sports Day (NGWSD), and GoGirlGo! events, are documented over time in event programs and planning materials. Files date from 1974 to 2018.
    Files are arranged chronologically and maintained in original order from the WSF office. At the end of the chronological run, as well as dispersed throughout the files, several individual folders appear out of chronological order. This potential mis-filing of folders has been maintained as the materials arrived.
    - Women's Sports subscription offer, 1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Philosophy and statement of purpose, 1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - WomenSports subscriber survey, 1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - College scholarship guide, 1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Affirmative Action program, 1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Seminars, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Newsletter, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      Contains Frontiers newsletter, Volume 1 number 1, 2, and 3.
    - Film proposal - The Importance of Sports, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Promotional, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - College scholarship guide, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Revlon Sports Skills, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Revlon Physical Conditioning Guide, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    - Revlon Publicity and Promotions Handbook, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    - Revlon Sport Organization Guide, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    - Revlon Title IX Guide, 1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newsletter, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    - Women in Motion, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    - Misc. proposals, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    - Running certification project, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    - College scholarship guide, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
    - Wade trophy, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
    - Challenge and choice dinners, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    - Newsletter, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    - The All-Star Salute to Women's Sports, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
    - Women's Sport posters [proposal], 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
    - Women's athletic club proposal, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
    - Camp scholarship program (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
    - Dance-A-Thon, 1978 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
    - Women's Sports magazine promotion, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
    - Newsletter, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
    - Amateur sports club proposal, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
    - Associate WSF New York, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
    - Associate WSF New York/ Westchester, 1979-1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
    - Associate WSF New Jersey, 1979-1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
    - Associate WSF New England, 1979-1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
    - Associate WSF Northwest, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
    - Associate WSF St. Louis, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
    - Membership promotion, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
    - Associations summaries, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 40)
    - Association leaders and letters, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 41)
    - College scholarship guide, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 42)
    - Wade trophy dinner, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 43)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 44)
    - Title IX President Carter, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 45)
    - Quarterly reports, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 46)
    - High school all star award, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 47)
    - Get into condition program, 1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 48)
    - Quarterly report, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - [Poster proposals], 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - Film proposal, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - College scholarship guide, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - [Grodins All Women's Run], 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    - New York Dinner, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    - Women's Sports subscriber survey, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    - Third annual Margaret Wade awards dinner, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    - Women's sport expo, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publicity proposal, 1980 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    - College scholarship guide, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    - Toyota Championships, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    - Quarterly report, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    - [Sportsline], 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    - Women's sports conference, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    - Nominating committee correspondence, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
    - Awards program, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    - NYAD, 1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    - Dinner (New York), 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
    - Annual report, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    - Proposal WSF national education and resource center, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
    - College scholarship guide, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
    - Nominating committee correspondence, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
    - Newsletter, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    - Baseball reunion, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
    - Peanuts poster, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    - Project MAP, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
    - Women's fitness sports med., 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
    - Women's Sports Hall of Fame, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
    - Coca Cola media tour, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
    - National fitness classic, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
    - Marketing proposal - Jill Wing, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
    - Tennis proposals, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
    - Women's sports clinics, 1982 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
    - New agenda conference, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 39)
    - Selection ballot - individual contribution, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 40)
    - Newsletter, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 41)
    - Awards, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 42)
    - Drummond estate, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 43)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 44)
    - California raisin advisory board, 1983 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 45)
    - Himalayan expedition, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ocean Spray, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    - College scholarship guide, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    - Nightline women in sports, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    - Publicity and promotion handbook, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Over 30's tennis classic, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    - Careers guide, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    - Women's fitness/ sports med., 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    - Special programs, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    - National fitness clinic, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    - New agenda, 1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    - The graphic art of Charles Schulz, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    - E. Auchincloss speech re: effectiveness Title IX, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    - Olympics promotion, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    - Women's fitness and health program, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
    - High school all-star winners, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
    - Women's sports hall of fame, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    - Camp scholarship program, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    - College scholarship guide, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    - Awards program, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
    - Annual report, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
    - Associate British WSF, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
    - Newsletter, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
    - Personal products, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
    - The role and place of sport and fitness in the lives of American women: a scientific study, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25)
    - Tribute to Esther Williams, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hogathon, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 27)
    - Women's fitness invitational, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
    - Women's marathon celebration, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
    - Women in motion, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
    - Fund raising campaign, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
    - Athletic games with California beef council, 1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
    - Aspire higher, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
    - An evening of achievement, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    - New York dinner, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
    - High school all-star winners, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
    - College scholarship guide, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
    - Camp guide/ scholarships, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
    - California beef council, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
    - Car council, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
    - Coupon ads, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 41)
    - Publicity NYAP, 1985 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42)
    - The financial district strut, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    - Women's sports and fitness, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    - Resource materials, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    - Newsletter, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    - Revlon award, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    - Annual report, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    - Miller Lite report, 1985 December (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
    - The greatest American athlete of the last 25 years, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
    - Awards program production, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
    - Speaker's bureau, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
    - The strength within: health and fitness, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    - Women's sports alliance Marin City, California, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
    - Public relations/ marketing, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    - Awards program, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
    - Headway newsletter, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    - A salute to women in sports, 1986 September (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
    - Book/ video club, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    - Strategies for success, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    - Internship program, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    - New agenda, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    - New York dinner, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    - Levi Strauss contribution award, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
    - Milky way high school all-star awards, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
    - Women's sports and fitness qualitative research study, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    - Ocean Spray, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    - Scholarship guide, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
    - Women's sports hall of fame, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    - Up and coming award winners, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
    - CAR (Coaches' Advisory Roundtable), 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
    - Travel and training fund, 1986 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
    - New agenda, 1987 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
    - New agenda II, 1987 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    - National girls and women in sports day, 1987 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
    - Awards program, 1987 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
    - Parents guide to girls in sports, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Annual report, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    - Aspire higher search, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    - Journalism awards, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - NY dinner, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Challenge of the champions, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    - Challenge media packets, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    - DAY clips, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    - Intercollegiate athletics for women The University of Texas at Austin, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    - Internship program, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    - Headway newsletter, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    - College scholarship guide, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    - Renewal-intent study, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    - Silent auction, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
    - Status of women's sports and role of LPGA, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
    - CAR [Coaches' Advisory Roundtable], 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
    - Aspire higher search, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
    - NGWSD, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
    - Summary of WSF activities, 1988 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)